<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tool id="reArraySubset" name="Subset Expression experiments">
<description>with BioConductor simpleaffy</description>
<code file="reMakeNew_code.py"/> 
<command interpreter="python">
reArraySubset.py '$i.extra_files_path' '$title' '$outhtml' '$outhtml.files_path'
 '$i.metadata.base_name' '$phename' '$phevals' '${GALAXY_DATA_INDEX_DIR}/rg/bin/R'
</command>
<inputs>
    <page>
        <param name="title" label="Title to label job output names" type="text" size="80" 
           value="Subset" />
        <param label="Genome" name="dbkey" type="select" dynamic_options="get_available_builds('hg18')" />
        <param name="i" type="data" format="affybatch,eset,malist" 
                label="Expression data set chosen from your history" optional="false"
                size="5"  />  
    </page>
    <page>
        <param name="phename"  type="select" display="radio" 
        label="Choose a phenodata column for selecting arrays for your subset" 
        dynamic_options="get_phecols(i)"  /> 
    </page>
    <page>
        <param name="phevals"  type="select" display="checkboxes" 
        label="Choose values for the selected phenodata column for the new subset"
        multiple="true" dynamic_options="get_phevals(i,phename)" /> 
    </page>
</inputs>

<outputs>  
    <data format='html' name="outhtml" />
</outputs>

 

<help>


**Syntax**

- **Title** is used to name the output files - so make it meaningful
- **History data file** is any Rexpression file with raw data (eg an affybatch) in your history 


-----

**Summary**

This tool uses BioC's Simpleaffy to compare two groups of arrays from an experiment. It takes 
either eSet or AffyBatch objects as input - use the History datatype changer to select the ones you want, then
choose one of those files as the input file from your current history.

You can choose one of the phenotype categories to analyse differences on - choose one that has two levels. Note that only
columns from the phenodata that have more than one value, but less values than there are chips will be displayed, and the
count of each distinct value will be shown after the column name.

Note that this tool uses ideas documented at
http://faculty.ucr.edu/~tgirke/Documents/R_BioCond/R_BioCondManual.html#biocon_affypack
and available along with a vast array of other, well maintained software at 
http://bioconductor.org 
Users should feel free to cite the web address of this tool, 
and as many of the other responsible contributers as will fit, since your results
depend on the work of a very large number of other people. 
It was designed and written for the Rexpression BioC/Galaxy tools by 
ross lazarus (ross d0t lazarus at gmail d0t com) August 2008
Copyright Ross Lazarus 2008
Licensed under the LGPL as documented at http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html


</help>
</tool>
