<tool id="rgLpedSubset1" name="Import and subset lped">
  <description>from syslib into Plink binary format</description>
<command interpreter="python">
rgLpedSub.py '$i' '$log' '$log.extra_files_path' '$region' '$rslist' 
</command>

<inputs>
    <param name="i" label="Select data to subset and convert" type="select" 
    size="200" dynamic_options="get_available_data('lped')" />
    <param label="Genome" name="dbkey" type="select" dynamic_options="get_available_builds('hg18')" />

    <param name="region" type="text" label="Genomic refseq coordinates - chromosome:start-end" 
    size="120" help="Leave blank to use rslist below otherwise region egchr9:119,506,000-119,518,000"/>

    <param name="rslist" type="text" area='true' size='15x20' label="marker id (rs) list"
    help="Leave blank for region, else cut and paste, or type a list of marker ids in --snps format - see below"  />    

</inputs>
<outputs>
<data format="txt" name="log"/>
</outputs>
<code file="rgLpedSub_code.py"/>
<help>

.. class:: infomark

**Notes on parameters**

- **File to import** Choose a file from the files made available by your system administrator of the type specified 
- **Title** Will appear in drop down lists so should be a meaningful brief name

-----

**Summary**


This tool allows you to import new data sets into your current history from a library of files made available
by your system administrator - the files must be placed in a specific place on the filesystem to appear here

The input file can be selected from available lped files. The new file in your history will be a plink internal binary
file set of the same base name

Leave both range and rslist blank to convert the entire input data set.
To filter by region, supply one in ucsc format as suggested above

The Plink documentation for the alternative rs number list format is as follows:

    Alternatively, the newer --snps command is more flexible but slower than the previously described
    --snp and --from/--to commands. The --snps command will accept a comma-delimited list of SNPs,
    including ranges based on physical position. For example,
    plink --bfile mydata --snps rs273744-rs89883,rs12345-rs67890,rs999,rs222
    selects the same range as above (rs273744 to rs89883) but also the separate range rs273744 to rs89883
    as well as the two individual SNPs rs999 and rs222. Note that SNPs need not be on the same chromosome;
    also, a range can span multiple chromosomes (the range is defined based on chromosome code order in that case,
    as well as physical position, i.e. a range from a SNP on chromosome 4 to one on chromosome 6 includes all SNPs on chromosome 5).



-----

.. class:: infomark

**Attribution**
Originally designed and written for the Rgenetics
series of Galaxy tools by Dan Blankenberg and modified
by ross lazarus (ross.lazarus@gmail.com), who didn't write Galaxy
but wishes he had.

This tool uses Plink (http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/plink/index.shtml) to create a Plink format binary  
file for other rgenetics tools.

</help>
</tool>
